<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Teares for the neuer sufficientlie bewailed death of the late right honourable and most worthie of all honourable titles, Alexander Earle of Dumfermeling, Lord Fyuie, and Vrquhart late Lord Chancellar of Scotland</title>
            <author>Lyon, John, fl. 1608-1622.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109753</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845399</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845399</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10296</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10296)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 850:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Teares for the neuer sufficientlie bewailed death of the late right honourable and most worthie of all honourable titles, Alexander Earle of Dumfermeling, Lord Fyuie, and Vrquhart late Lord Chancellar of Scotland</title>
                  <author>Lyon, John, fl. 1608-1622.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the heires of Andro Hart,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Dom. 1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: John Lyoun.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dunfermline, Alexander Seton, --  Earl of, 1555-1622 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10296:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 134 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10296:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 134 -->
            <p>TEARES For the neuer ſufficientlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailed death of the late right <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and moſt worthie of</hi> all honourable Titles, ALEXANDER EARLE of <hi>Dumfermeling,</hi> Lord <hi>Fyuie,</hi> and Vrquhart late <hi>Lord Chancellar of</hi> SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>EDINBVRGH, Printed by the Heires of ANDRO HART.</p>
            <p>ANNO DOM. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:10296:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 135 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:10296:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 135 -->
            <head>TO MY VERIE Honourable and moſt reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>good LADIE,</hi> Dame <hi>Beatrix Ruthven,</hi> LADIE <hi>Coldenknowes.</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S I condemne the vnnaturall custome of the Auntient <hi>Thracians,</hi> who vſed to weepe at the birth of their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and to rejoyce at the death of their Parents, Kins-folke, and Friends: So I can not but commend your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhips firm-fixt affection to your friends, which (contrarie to the common cuſtome of this time-ſeruing Age) Death doeth not diminiſh which your La. makes manifeſt at this time, for no ſooner had fame<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> filled the eares of all, with the ſorrowfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, of the neuer ſufficientlie bewailed death of the late right honourable Lord Chancellar: but your La. to ſhow, that as in this generall loſſe your loſſe was more then commone, hauing loſt ſo honourable a Patrone, ſo faithfull a Friend, and ſo louing a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in all your affaires: ſo you in ſorrow exceeded the moſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull,
<pb facs="tcp:10296:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 136 -->your La. repledged from the fire, this vnpoliſht ryme, to the which (as vnworthie of the worlds view) I condemned the ſame, and cauſ'd the ſame ſo bee printed: to the which I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcended, willing rather to publiſh mine owne imperfections them that your La. ſcarce imitable and vnfained affection to that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Lord ſhould bee concealed, accept then (Madam) in good part thoſe lines which by your owne procurment paſſes to the Preſſe and as they beare the badges of your Ladiſhips ſorrow for your ſo great a loſſe, let them ſerue as ſignes to ſhow the willingnes I haue to doe your Ladiſhip all the ſeruice I can performe, to the which I am tyed both by bandes of blood and nature, and by your Ladiſhips manifold vndeſerued courteous fauours to my ſelfe, hoping that the Title of your Ladiſhippes name ſhall ſeruee as a ſufficient defence for all the imperfections of thoſe vnperfect and vnpoliſht lines, kiſſing your Ladiſhips hands I reſt, and ſhall euer remaine.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips Couſen moſt humblie devoted to ſerue you <hi>John Lyoun.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:10296:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 136 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>Tudor rose</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>a blazon with the monogram of 'A' (Andro) superimposed on ♡ (Hart)</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>Scottish thistle</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>TEARES For the neuer ſufficiently bewailed death <hi>of the late right honourable and moſt</hi> worthie of all honourable Titles, ALEXANDER EARLE of <hi>Dumfermeling,</hi> Lord <hi>Fyuie,</hi> and Vrquhart late <hi>Lord Chancellar of</hi> SCOTLAND.</head>
            <l>AH, muſt my weake and care-benummed hand,</l>
            <l>Paint out the ſorrowes of this ſorrowing Land:</l>
            <l>How can my pen make others paſſions knowne,</l>
            <l>Which as they are, can not expreſſe mine owne:</l>
            <l>This publike loſſe, which was a loſſe too great,</l>
            <l>Some heauen-taught Muſe were fitter to relate:</l>
            <l>Yet whilſt the Learned (who in ſilence fit)</l>
            <l>Frame loftie Lynes to ſerue as ſignes of wit.</l>
            <l>Sad care-croſt Muſe vnto the world proclaime,</l>
            <l>With wofull notes this lamentable Theame:</l>
            <l>And ſing ſo ſadlie to each liſtning eare,</l>
            <l>That euerie eye for tribute pay a teare.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:10296:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 137 -->
Come euerie Age, Eſtate, and Sexe, come all,</l>
            <l>Come and bewaile this ſtatelie Cedars fall.</l>
            <l>Come all wrong'd <hi>Orphanes,</hi> come bewaile your ſyre,</l>
            <l>Who did of late (but yet too ſoone) expyre,</l>
            <l>Come woefull widowes, come you, weepe you faſt,</l>
            <l>Your Anchor, and your hope, your helpe is paſt.</l>
            <l>Rich Burgers your of whom hee once was chiefe,</l>
            <l>With teares bewray vnto the world your griefe,</l>
            <l>You at the Barre who pleade your clients cauſe,</l>
            <l>Mourne that ye want the Iudge that judg'd your Lawes,</l>
            <l>Graue learned Iudges all burſt foorth in mone,</l>
            <l>Your Light, your Lanterne and your Guide is gone,</l>
            <l>State-ruling Peeres, true pillers of the Crowne,</l>
            <l>Fit for <hi>Bellona,</hi> or the peacefull gownc.</l>
            <l>Helpe to be-waile that euer-famous Lord,</l>
            <l>Whoſe noble partes nobilitie decor'd:</l>
            <l>The heauens themſelues as murners doe prepare,</l>
            <l>With ſignes of ſorrow to increaſe our care.</l>
            <l>For when hee dy'd, the heauens on earth did powre,</l>
            <l>Greiu'd at his death, of teares a liberall ſhowre.</l>
            <l>And ere hee dy'd, <hi>Latona's</hi> child ſo bright</l>
            <l>Crab-like retired from his Sphears chiefe hight.</l>
            <l>As if hee would to euerie one bewray,</l>
            <l>In humane ſhape an heauenlie lightes decay.</l>
            <l>For hee, as where his fooliſh ſonne did guide</l>
            <l>The head-ſtrong horſes hee was wont to ride,</l>
            <l>Obſcures his rayes and hides his glorious eye,</l>
            <l>Loathe on the earth, this woefull ſight to ſee.</l>
            <l>Our Day did ſet when wee expected leaſt,</l>
            <l>Our Light, when full and at the higheſt, ceaſt.</l>
            <l>Our Summer ended, or it halfe was done,</l>
            <l>For loe, it ended in the midſt of <hi>Iune.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:10296:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 137 -->
For with his date, our joyes receiued theirs,</l>
            <l>His dulefull death gaue life vnto our cares.</l>
            <l>Speake tyrant Death, ſhew if thou canſt wherefore</l>
            <l>Thou ſpoil'd the Stone that did our ring decore?</l>
            <l>Did not of late each State a tribute pay?</l>
            <l>Did not each-where thy crueltie beare ſway?</l>
            <l>Peeres, Church-men, Iudges all did tribute giue,</l>
            <l>And were content ſo hee alone might liue.</l>
            <l>But thou inſatiate monſter who is gladde,</l>
            <l>To ſee the world ſtrooke with amazement ſadde.</l>
            <l>In this thou preaſt thy powerfull force to ſhow,</l>
            <l>Hurling all States by giuing ſuch a blow.</l>
            <l>Yet doe thy worſt, in ſpite of Time and Thee,</l>
            <l>His beſt partes ſtill ſhall liue and neuer die.</l>
            <l>His ſoule which from the Heauens to Earth deſcended,</l>
            <l>Bake from the Earth is to the Heauens aſcended.</l>
            <l>There ſtill to liue with that great KING of Kings,</l>
            <l>Where Angels euer Halleluiah ſings.</l>
            <l>And heere on earth ſtill famous ſhall remaine,</l>
            <l>His famous Acts in ſpight of Times diſdaine.</l>
            <l>No Marble, Porphire, Gold, Corinthiane Braſſe,</l>
            <l>Or Monument yet halfe ſo laſting was.</l>
            <l>Proud Pyramids of Artemiſian frame,</l>
            <l>Vaine Monuments of quicke decaying fame,</l>
            <l>Will with their builders periſh and decay,</l>
            <l>That where they ſtood ſcarce comming time can ſay,</l>
            <l>But hee more wiſe hath built a Tombe more ſtrong,</l>
            <l>Which ſtill ſhall laſt, in ſpight of Envies wrong,</l>
            <l>Trueth, Iuſtice, Mercie, Policie, and Peace,</l>
            <l>Shall this rare Hero's Tombe with dicton grace,</l>
            <l>For Trueth ſhall ſay (and Trueth can neuer lie)</l>
            <l>His rare true worth vnparalel'd ſhall bee.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:10296:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 138 -->
Iuſtice and Mercie fitting for a Iudge,</l>
            <l>Hee wiſelie mixt and in his breaſt did Iudge:</l>
            <l>Iuſtice to none hee neuer did refuſe,</l>
            <l>Yet did ſterne Law with mercie of times vſe,</l>
            <l>That Pylian Sage, of whom his Ruler ſaide,</l>
            <l>Troy could not ſtand, if but ten ſuch hee had,</l>
            <l>Might well bee ſpar'd, did hee in Counſell ſit,</l>
            <l>Whoſe rypned Iudgement led each younger wit.</l>
            <l>And as on Hybla or Hymetus Hill,</l>
            <l>The hony Birdes the flowrie mountaines fill.</l>
            <l>Searching from graſſe to graſſe, from flower to flower,</l>
            <l>To bring their ſweete foode to their ſweetned Bower.</l>
            <l>Looke to the trauell of his younger yeares,</l>
            <l>And like to thoſe his policie appeares:</l>
            <l>For loe, hee Bee-like paſt from place to place,</l>
            <l>Knowledge to gaine which might his Countrie grace,</l>
            <l>Paines, trauell, hazard, hee eſteemed nought,</l>
            <l>To gaine the wiſh'd for knowledge which hee ſought.</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Loire, Seine,</hi> and <hi>Rhine,</hi> with <hi>Tiber, Arne,</hi> and <hi>Poe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Their Bankes hee paſt to make his learning growe,</l>
            <l>And as the Bee from euerie flower doth take,</l>
            <l>The ſweeteſt juice his pleaſing food to make.</l>
            <l>Wherewith full fraught hee haſtes him to his Hyue,</l>
            <l>Where Drones decay, but thriſtie Bees doe thryue.</l>
            <l>So in his trauels with judicious eye,</l>
            <l>Hee did the beſt of forraine partes eſpie,</l>
            <l>And what in vertues Gardens hee found rare,</l>
            <l>Hee brought them home, and made them flouriſh faire.</l>
            <l>Which made his Prince (true Iudge of noble parts,</l>
            <l>Sole cheriſher of vertue, worth and arts)</l>
            <l>To raiſe this Lord vpon the Stage of State,</l>
            <l>To ſhow his wit in Iudgements higheſt ſeate.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:10296:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 138 -->
VVhere whilſt hee ſpake with judgement, wit, and Art,</l>
            <l>Hee raviſh'd euerie eare, and euerie heart:</l>
            <l>His wiſe graue ſentences ſo each man mou'd,</l>
            <l>Hee was of all admir'd, of all belou'd.</l>
            <l>That ſcarce this envious world afforded one,</l>
            <l>That for his greatneſſe greeu'd, e'er gaue a grone.</l>
            <l>O wonder rare! moſt wonderfull to ſee,</l>
            <l>A States-man great, and welbelou'd to bee:</l>
            <l>Yet hee his greatneſſe manag'd with ſuch skill,</l>
            <l>As hee heap'tvp huge treaſure of good-will.</l>
            <l>VVhich now is knowne, for now each one may ſpye,</l>
            <l>VVhat ſecret thought, in euerie breaſt did lye,</l>
            <l>For loe, the State grieues at this publike loſſe,</l>
            <l>Each priuate man thinkes this a priuate croſſe.</l>
            <l>That greatneſſe gone (which as ſome man did thinke,</l>
            <l>Might make hid malice in ſome boſome ſhrinke)</l>
            <l>There's none that liues, or breathes this common aire,</l>
            <l>But for his death ſeemes ouercome with care.</l>
            <l>And reaſon would it that it ſhould bee ſo,</l>
            <l>Since publike good did from his greatneſſe grow.</l>
            <l>His chiefe deſignes were for the Common-good,</l>
            <l>VVhich who ſo croſt his counſell ſtill with-ſtood.</l>
            <l>Yet Princes fauour, honour, vertue, loue,</l>
            <l>Could not ſterne Death to mild compaſſion moue.</l>
            <l>O blind and deafe inſatiat monſter Death,</l>
            <l>Had thou had ſeene when as thou rob'd his breath,</l>
            <l>His Ladies beautie or her carefull cryes,</l>
            <l>Had pearc't thine eare, or mou'd thine hood-winkt eyes,</l>
            <l>His Friendes complaints, his Childrens ruthfull teares,</l>
            <l>Did plead for pittie at thy deafned eares.</l>
            <l>Yet nought could ſtay thine hand from ſuch a deed,</l>
            <l>As makes our heartes with woefull wounds to bleed.</l>
            <l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:10296:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 139 -->
For Heauens decree this judgement giues to all,</l>
            <l>That Prince and Peaſant both by Death ſhall fall:</l>
            <l>Since Deathes ſtraite doome can bee eſchew'd of none,</l>
            <l>VVhy for his death ſhould wee ſigh, weepe, and grone?</l>
            <l>For wee did know when as hee was moſt hye,</l>
            <l>That hee was mortall, and was borne to dye.</l>
            <l>And thus to grudge againſt IEHOVAHS will,</l>
            <l>May bring on vs a farre more greater ill.</l>
            <l>And well wee know, hee dy'de to liue againe,</l>
            <l>His death was but a period to his paine.</l>
            <l>VVee grudge not gainſt the Architect of wonders,</l>
            <l>VVhoſe fearfull voyce ſpeakes in the mids of thunders.</l>
            <l>VVee onelie waile to teſtifie our loue,</l>
            <l>For his perfections did affection moue.</l>
            <l>Thoſe peereleſſe parts hee liuing did inherite,</l>
            <l>Now beeing dead, this at our hands doth merite.</l>
            <l>That as our bakes this badge of mourning beares,</l>
            <l>VVee ſhould to Griefe pay tribute with our teares.</l>
            <l>But ah, my Muſe breake off and come away,</l>
            <l>Thou ſhowes too much of this our ſad decay,</l>
            <l>Let brauer wits this deepe taske vnder-goe.</l>
            <l>To waile his want and manifeſt our woe.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:10296:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 139 -->
            <head>Lifes vncertaintie.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BEhold vaine man how fraile a thing thou art,</l>
               <l>Proud of a puffe, of ſoone conſumed breath:</l>
               <l>Which with a blaſt will ſuddenlie depart,</l>
               <l>When thou art cited by deuouring death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thy Pride, thy State, thine Honour, Blood &amp; Gold,</l>
               <l>Can not Deaths ſtroak one minuts ſpace with-hold</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Count from thy Cradle euen vnto thy Tombe,</l>
               <l>And thou ſhalt find Life but a Mappe of cares.</l>
               <l>For when thou firſt comes from thy Mothers wombe,</l>
               <l>Thy lifes firſt minut it is ſpent in teares,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As if when borne thou did perfeclie know</l>
               <l>That thou waſt borne to beare a birth of woe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And if more yeeres thou happen to attaine,</l>
               <l>Thy griefe ſhall grow ſtill as thy yeeres increaſſe,</l>
               <l>The moe thy dayes, the more ſhall bee thy paine,</l>
               <l>Few dayes ſhall paſſe without a new diſtreſſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Friends, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rents, Children, Kins-folk, credits loſſe,</l>
               <l>Or ſome ſuch care ſhall ſtill increaſe thy woes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yea, if the World w<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ld poure into thy lappe,</l>
               <l>Her richeſt treaſures in a liberall ſhoure,</l>
               <l>Yet thinke not much of this imagin'd happe,</l>
               <l>Which may bee ſpent, or periſh in an houre.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Earths flying joyes are like a ſummer field,</l>
               <l>Whoſe bloſſomes muſt to flower-quell winter yeild</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Imagine this (which to bee found is rare,</l>
               <l>Thy joyes were neuer interrupt with griefe,</l>
               <l>Thy life-time ſpent without a dram of care,</l>
               <l>Yet at the laſt Death like a ſubtill Thiefe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:10296:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 140 -->
               <l>Will ſteal thy joyes, which is a fading treaſure,</l>
               <l>To make thee know how periſhing is pleaſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Life which the Worldings doe ſo much adore:</l>
               <l>Is like a dreame, a blaſt of wauering wind,</l>
               <l>A ſhade, a ſpan, a ſmoake, an airie ſtore,</l>
               <l>A gulfe of griefe, where few contentment find.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A ſea of ſorrows and a ſhip of toyes,</l>
               <l>Fraught full of certaine cares, vncertaine joyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Since life is ſuch, then let vs learne to die,</l>
               <l>That wee by death a better life may gaine,</l>
               <l>Let vs this Scilla this Charibdis flee,</l>
               <l>Haſte to the port and flee the troubled Maine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where wee ſhall finde contentment, and till then,</l>
               <l>No true contentment is to mortall men.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:10296:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 140 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
